<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Scotland mourning: or, A short discovery of the sad consequences which accompanies the delay of the setling judicatories in that nation. By Robert Pittilloh advocate.</title>
            <author>Pittilloh, Robert, 1621?-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54943</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2312</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218256</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829866</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829866</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34312</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54943)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34312)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2011:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Scotland mourning: or, A short discovery of the sad consequences which accompanies the delay of the setling judicatories in that nation. By Robert Pittilloh advocate.</title>
                  <author>Pittilloh, Robert, 1621?-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year 1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Robert Pittillok, i.e. Pittilloh.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  History --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34312:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SCOTLAND MOURNING: OR, A Short DISCOVERY <hi>OF THE</hi> Sad CONSEQUENCES Which accompanies the Delay of the ſetling Judicatories in that NATION.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Robert Pittilloh</hi> Advocate.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 CHRON. 22.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Ariſe therefore, and be doing, and the Lord be with thee.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ESTHER 4.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I will go in, which is not according to law, and if I periſh, I periſh.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the year 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:34312:2"/>
            <head>SCOTLAND MOURNING: <hi>OR,</hi> A ſhort Diſcovery of the Sad Conſequences which accompanies the delay of the ſetling Judicatories in that Nation.</head>
            <p>TO every thing there is a ſeaſon and a time to every pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe under the Heaven, ſaith the Wiſeman, and among other things a time to keep ſilence, and a time to ſpeak: And if ever there was a fit time to ſpeak, it is when the Cauſe of the Dumb is pleaded, and iniquity not only done: But when there is hazard that it ſhall be eſtabliſhed by a Law; If full information be not given concerning the truth of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs: The conſideration whereof makes me look upon it as my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at this time to give a word of Information to the Supream Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, concerning the deſolate condition of the Nation of <hi>Scotland,</hi> by want of Juſtice, and the ſad affliction, it ſhould further under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe, if the ſetling of Judicatories ſhall be delayed for any long ſpace: upon cloſing of the Union of any other pretence whatſoever. It may ſeem to ſome impertinent for me to uſe ſuch freedome in ſo high a concernment; but beſide that, every member of the body, albeit, the meaneſt ought naturally to care for the good of the whole; in time of a dangerous Tempeſt, every Paſſenger in a Ship ought to put to his hand; and albeit in a Calme, his ſervice would have been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted Officious, yet in ſuch a caſe when the Storme is over, if he have been inſtrumentall in preſerving the Ship, none will defraud him of his deſerved Commendation. I am not ignorant of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and hatred it may procure, at the hands of ſome of my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen here; knowing how much ſome of them have already ſmitten me with the Tongue, making their Arrowes flye in ſecred upon groundleſs imaginations againſt me: and if I durſt follow the prudentiall conſideration of ſelf intereſt, I ſhould put my Seal to whatſoever they ſay; but when I conſider that the fearfull and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing ſhall receive the ſame diſpenſations of wrath from God: And that <hi>Job</hi> reckons it among the chief of his vindications from the Calumnies of his Friends, did I fear a great multitude, or did, the contempt of Families terrifie me, that I kept ſilence, and went not out of the Doore: I am taught intentionally not to do any thing againſt the Truth, but for the Truth; neither ſhall I write any thing which juſtly may give offence to any ſober ſpirit, knowing that men may be of different apprehenſions, being all of pure hearts
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34312:2"/>and innocent hands: and if by this, Truth all ſhall be diſcovered Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of Truth, will rejoyce therein, if otherwiſe, I have but loſt my labour, and publiſhed my own weakneſs.</p>
            <p>The thing to be conſidered is, <hi>Whether it be fit and expedient to delay the ſetling of the Courts of Juſtice, in</hi> Scotland, <hi>and Officers neceſſary, for carrying on the Adminiſtration of Juſtice before them, till the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion betwixt</hi> Scotland <hi>and</hi> England <hi>be cloſed or not.</hi>] The Negative we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for.</p>
            <p>For clearing whereof, we ſhall firſt examine the meaning of this expedient, ſecondly the reaſons thereof, and thridly remonſtrate the many ſad conſequences that accompany it, which ſhall be as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Arguments againſt it. As to the firſt, The meaning and ſence of it cannot be, till the Parliament ratifie and confirm the Act of Union paſt in the time of the late Protector, Becauſe it is humbly conceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, neither could it ſtand with the honour of the Parliament, <hi>ſide im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicita,</hi> to ratifie that Act, nor if it had been intended, would the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament or their Counſell have made any reference to Scotſmen, for conſidering the expediency of the ſetling Judicatories, before or after the cloſing thereof: nor had it b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n wothy their conſultation, ſeeing it is obvious to the meaneſt capacity, that an Act of ratification of this nature, and for ſetling of Judicatories, might have been paſt in one and the ſelf ſame day at different houres, after they were prepar'd. The true and genuine ſence of it then muſt be, till the Union betwixt the two Nations be cloſed in a legall and ſolid way, to the rationall ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of both. For effectuating whereof, It is humbly conceived, 1. Commiſſioners lawfully choſen muſt come from <hi>Scotland</hi> for Treating of the matter, or meet with Commiſioners of Parliament upon the place appointed by them for that Effect For to paſs an Act of Union without their conſtent, were to make a forced Marriage with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſent of Parties; and if any in their name ſhould conſent, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Commiſſion, ſuch couſent would be <hi>ipſo jure null,</hi> as to the thing, and <hi>crimen falſe,</hi> in a high degree to the Actors. 2. Examination of the legall elections and qualifications, for <hi>non fieri &amp; non rite fieri in jure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>parificantur.</hi> 3. The matter muſt be debated, and conditions of the Union held forth pondered, and accepted, and if Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Parliament ſhall be ſent to <hi>Scotland</hi> for that purpoſe, if any thing fall out dubious, expreſſes muſt be ſent up to the Parliament for reſolution, for the anſwers whereof they muſt wait before they bring the matter to a period. 4. The Act muſt be prepared and paſt. Laſtly, Before writes can be emitted in name of <hi>the keepers of the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of England and Scotland</hi> Commiſſioners, from <hi>Scotland</hi> lawfully choſen by warrant of the Parliament, muſt be ſet down in Parliament as ſharers in the Authority. For it ſeems contrary to Law and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> can be cald keepers of the liberty of <hi>Scotland,</hi> till Members of that Nation be a part of their number, having an intrinſick repugnance in it ſelf, in ſo far as it is to them
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34312:3"/>meerly a Provinciall Government, Diametrally oppoſit to the liberty of a free People, to be governed only by the repreſentatives of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nation. There being as yet no Order of Parliament Iſſued forth for choſing Commiſſioners in <hi>Scotland,</hi> for Treating of the Union, nor Commiſſioners of Parliament appointed, (if it ſhall be found need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,) to meet with them upon the place, the Journey being long, the matter weighty, and of great concernment, the Perſons intereſted many, of various Judgments, and different abilities; with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dilatory circumſtances conſidered: It cannot in reaſon be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, that before the expiring of five or ſix Moneths time, albeit gone about with the greateſt alacrity, the Uunion can be brought to ſuch perfection, as that Commiſſioners of <hi>Scotland</hi> lawfully choſen, may be ſitting in the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> without which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be cald <hi>keepers of the liberty of Scotland:</hi> beſides that it is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that the cloſing of this Union may be interrupted for at me, by unexpected emergencies: So that in plain engliſh, the ſenſe of it in it ſelf is, <hi>It is fit and expedient to delay the ſetting of the Courts of Juſtice in Scotland,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>as yet for five or ſix Moneths in coming, and if at that time the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion be not cloſed; that accordingly this be delayed,</hi> albeit I am ſo charitable as to believe it is not intended by thoſe who are of this Judgment, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it ſhall be for ſo long a ſpace.</p>
            <p>But it may be obiected the Parliament may cloſe the Union upon the conſent given by the Commiſſioners for <hi>Scotland,</hi> in Anno. 1652. To which it is anſwered, 1. <hi>Quod poſſibile eſt eſſe poſſibile eſt non eſſe.</hi> 2. Thoſe who chooſe wiſely among probables, conſider that which is moſt probable as the ground of her actings; and we humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, it is more probable the Parliament will not cloſe the Union up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that conſent for theſe reaſons. Firſt, Though it be the ſame Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament and Authority that then was, yet virtually and conſequentially the conſent ſeems to be interrupted, in ſo far as it was to <hi>[their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners,]</hi> becauſe of the Act of Union, paſt by the ſingle Perſon, wherein <hi>Scotland</hi> was forced to acquieſſe, having no power to reſiſt. 2. That conſent being now near ſeaven years old, cannot be preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be ſo effectuall for engaging <hi>Scotland</hi> cordially to concurre with <hi>England</hi> in the common concernment as it would be, being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed: if a man had ſo long been kept at a diſtance from his inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Wife, a more intimate renovation of their acquaintance, would be thought neceſſary before, the conſumation of the Marriage. 3. The exerciſe of the preſent Authority having been for ſo long a time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted, it is humbly conceived it will be found neceſſary that by a new conſent, <hi>Scotland</hi> do acknowledg the preſent Authority, and that they are lawfully again cald to the exerciſe thereof: Laſtly, The nature and conditions of the Union having never as yet been exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and approved by the preſent Parliament, when they fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the debate, if it ſhall be found neceſſary that any thing therein be altered, or that any new thing be added thereto without new
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34312:3"/>repreſentatives of the Nation, they have none to confer with about the ſame.</p>
            <p>The ſecond particular is the foundation whereon this expedient is built, or the Arguments brought for ſtrengthening of it, which, ſo far as we can learn, are. 1. It would be a means to cauſe the Union to be ſlighted, forgotten, or delayed. 2. It is not fit, Writs in <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhould be emitted in name of the keepers of the liberties of <hi>England,</hi> but <hi>Scotland</hi> alſo. To the firſt it is anſwered, If the ſetling of Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories be a ground of ſlighting or delaying the Union, it muſt be ſo ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Parliament or People of <hi>Scotland,</hi> but neither can rational<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſaid, <hi>ergo,</hi> &amp;c. not the firſt, becauſe according to the Principles both of reaſon and ſound Divinity, the performing of one duty is ſo far from indiſpoſing them for the performance of another, that it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther habituats, and further enables them for a ſecond: ſo that it were bad Logick ſo to reaſon, becauſe the Parliament hath done one duty to <hi>Scotland,</hi> therefore they will neglect another. They muſt pardon me, to ſay they have hard thoughts of the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſon who fears the delay of the union becauſe of the ſetling of Judicatories there, when their Army in <hi>Anno</hi> 1650. (whom they then did and to this day do own) declared in <hi>Scotland, Their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences did bear them record, they did above any thing in the world de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the union of the two Nations: and that it was their daily prayer, that thoſe that feared the Lord in</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland, <hi>might become one in the hand of the Lord, and joyn together in the advancement of the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, and throwing down and trampling upon the ſeat of the Beaſt:</hi> And when in order to the ſetling of this union, the preſent Parliament in <hi>Anno</hi> 1652, with the firſt convenience, ſent their Commiſſioners to <hi>Scotland</hi> for that effect; Not the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; Firſt, Becauſe it cannot be imagined that the people of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> will be averſe from the union: are any people ſo fooliſh, as to chooſe rather to be a Province than a free people? Secondly, It is evident in reaſon, the more <hi>favours</hi> the Parliament confers upon them, the more cordiall they will be in the union, and cheerfull thereto, the greater lovelineſs one extream perceives in the other, the larger deſire it hath to be united thereto. To the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond it is anſwered; It cannot be conceived where the difficulty lieth, for either it muſt be becauſe of the indignity <hi>Scotland</hi> ſuſtains, by iſſuing forth Writs in name of the Keepers of the Liberty of <hi>England;</hi> or becauſe ſome confuſion will follow upon the change, when the union is cloſed. The firſt cannot be alleaged, for theſe reaſons; Firſt, the overturning of the Government in a ſingle Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon having taken the originall of it here, it is no indignity for <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to emit Writs in name of the Keepers of the Liberty of <hi>England,</hi> till they may likewiſe with Commiſſioners from <hi>Scotland,</hi> become Keepers of the Liberties of <hi>Scotland,</hi> it being impoſſible it ſhould be otherwiſe for the time. Secondly, It is known to all <hi>England</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:34312:4"/>and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and many hundreds of thouſands more, that <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is now under the power of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> as the only ſupream Authority, which rules and governs them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore emitting Writs which will never be publiſhed in any place but in their own Nation, can be neither an addition to, nor publication of this condition. Thirdly, It is but the continuing Writs in that ſame form they were in in <hi>Anno</hi> 1632; and thereafter till the ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the late Protector. Fourthly, It is but the emitting Writs in that ſame form for the peoples good and advantage, wherein Orders of their <hi>ſuffering</hi> for payment of <hi>Cuſtom, Seſs</hi> and <hi>Excize</hi> are emitted. Fiftly, There can be no more abſurdity for Writs to be iſſued forth in name of the Keepers of the Liberty of <hi>England,</hi> than for Sheriffs and Juſtices of Peace to keep Courts in <hi>Scotland</hi> in their name, <hi>magis &amp; minus non variant speciem:</hi> As to the ſecond it is cleer, no confuſion of Proceſs or other Writs whatſoever, can fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low upon change of the Style when the union ſhall be cloſed by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer experience, in ſo far as at the erection of the deceaſed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, no man who had a ſummons executed in name of the Keepers of the Liberty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was ever put to the renewing of them, nor any who had an Execution upon a Charge, put to the renewing of his Letters; yea which is further, no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon who had an Action depending in the late Kings time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lords of Seſſion, was put to that trouble as to begin the ſame <hi>de novo,</hi> before the Commiſſioners for adminiſtration of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, but only to waken it, notwithſtanding the change of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>As to the third, beſides many particulars which I will not enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merate, there are theſe ſad conſequences following clearly upon the delay: Firſt, If Judicatories be not ſetled before the firſt of <hi>November</hi> (which is the time of the down ſitting of the winter Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or Terme in <hi>Scotland,</hi>) neither Judges, Advocates nor Clarks, will be in readineſs for their employments, nor people throughout the Nation attending for Juſtice, by reaſon of the uncertainty of the ſitting of the Courts, whereby, albeit there were nothing more, that Seſſion for a great part will be rendered uneffectuall: and if it be delayed a moneth or two longer, altogether uſeleſs. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, There will be little work prepared for them, albeit both parties and Officers of Court were preſent, in ſo far as there are neither Judges having power to grant deliverances upon Bils, nor a Signet for granting ſummons, nor Meſſengers in all <hi>Scotland</hi> for executing; but after the Courts of Juſtice are ſetled, perſuers muſt firſt raiſe their ſummons; ſecondly, ſend Meſſengers at Arms to cite the defenders perſonally or at their dwelling places, giving them twenty ſeven free days before they be tied to compeer, betwixt the day of their citation and their compeerance, if within the Nation in moſt of Actions, beſides
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34312:4"/>the time which muſt be allowed to the Meſſenger for going to their dwellings, which in ſome parts of that Nation in ſtorms of the winter ſeaſon, may be as long: and 60 days if the defendant be without the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion after the citation, at the Market Croſs of <hi>Endenburrough</hi> Peer and ſhore of <hi>Leith.</hi> Thirdly, When they are returnd and called by the Clerks, the Defendant and his Advocate muſt have a competent time to ſee the purſuers Claim or Libell, and prepare him for the diſpute, where upon the ſame inconvenience formerly mentioned will follow.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, No perſon in <hi>Scotland</hi> can at this day charge his debtor to make payment of any ſomme of money or other duty reſting to him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Bond, Obligation or Contract, albeit there be many thouſands of that Nation in this condition, and many hundreds of Widows, Orphans, and fatherleſs Children, which have no other way for getting their bread: and generally the moſt part of all Creditors have been much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed from payment of their money, firſt by the late Act of Debitor and Creditor, ordaining them to take Land for their debts, and many there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after by the late Act taking of Forfeitures, ordaining their Creditors to quit a great part of their Intereſt, and take Land for their ſomme at a dear purchaſe: which might preſently be ſupplied by ſetling the Courts of Iuſtice and Officurs needfull for them: ſo that it is a groſs miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of affairs in a falſe glaſs, to affirm there is no need of ſetling theſe Courts till the time of the down ſitting of the winter Seſſion or Terme, in regard the Summer Terme is paſt, the prejudice which is ſuſtained by want of ezecution upon Bonds, Obligations and Contracts, being beyond that which is ſuſtained by want of a Seſſion or Terme, whereupon Creditors may have the ultimate of the Law, (if ſuſpenſion do not intervene) as fully and freely in time of vacancy, as in Terme time: Albeit now paying perſonall ſelf out of theſe Eſtates by Law, they are put in an incapacity of obtaining any perſonall eſtate either for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof or entertaining their own life by want of Law.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Albeit a Creditor ſee his Debtor diſpoſing or dilapidating his whole Eſtate, to the utter ruin of him and his family, he can neither ſerve Inhibition againſt him, nor appryſe from him, but with a forced patience muſt behold the deſtruction of himſelf and neereſt relations, in their worldly being: for which, ſetling of Judicatories as is beforeſaid will be a preſent remedy.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, The Sheriffs being the only perſons in that Nation at preſent authorized by the Parliament to ſit in Judgment in matters Civil; of whom ſome are ignorant, and others corrupt, (as witneſs the many ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations from them yearly, with the ſuſpenſions and reductions of their deceets paſt before the High Court of Juſtice,) have now power to carry on Proceſſes albeit incompetent for them, without contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and give our Decreits though never ſo wicked, without controle: and the ſuffering Defendant hath neither power to advocate his Action from them, while it is depending, nor to ſuſpend when it is decernd,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34312:5"/>but muſt ſit down in ſilence, ſuffering the Sheriffs Officer to poynd and take away his goods, albeit contrary to Juſtice, and the light of nature.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, No malefactor, of whoſe crimes the High Court of Juſtice in cauſes criminall is only Judg competent, can be convict, or brought to condign puniſhment, but muſt either eſcape free, or lie in priſon, to the great and unneceſſary burden of the people, the reproach of Juſtice, and encouragement of evil doers.</p>
            <p>Seaventhly, No perſon who ſtands in the greateſt hazard of his life, or eſtate, at the hands of his deſperate enemy, can get Letters of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourous for his ſecurity.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, All the publike Revenue payable to the Exchequer muſt ſleep in the hands of the debitors, and the publike Treaſury remain empty.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, That Nation being now put in confuſion by want of Juſtice, and hardly any way left to a great part of them how they ſhall get of their own for entertaining their naturall life, there can be no ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er inducement of new inſurrections thought upon, than the delay of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; deſparation being King of incendiaries; nor any mean more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing for enlarging their hearts in love to the preſent Authority, than a preſent ſetling of Judicatories among them. It had been better ſervice to God, to the Parliament and to the Nation, that ſome of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen who have been inſtrumentall in impeding the ſitting of the Summer Seſſion or Terme, had been uſefull for obtaining ſuch a ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſettlement, that <hi>Scotland</hi> with <hi>England</hi> might have been unſenſible of the interruption of Juſtice among them, upon the Alteration of the Government, and not put to mourn under their private ſufferings, when others are rejoycing in their publick Liberty.</p>
            <p>Theſe who reap the benefit of the delay, are the Outlaws, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digalls, waſters, the bankrupts, the oppreſſors, the lawleſs, the diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient, the Covenant breakers, the heady, the high-minded, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of thoſe things that are good. The ſufferers are the more frugall of the Country Gentlemen, the Merchants, and ſhopkeepers, the poor, the ſtranger, the fatherleſs and widow, the moſt conſcientious and ſober minded: and in refference to both, we ſhall ſay no more, but humbly remember the ſupream Authority of <hi>England,</hi> of two paſſages of the Declaration of their Army at <hi>Muſleborow</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1650. <hi>viz.</hi> pag. 5. <hi>We are poor unworthy inſtruments in Gods hand to break his enemies, and preſerve his people.</hi> And again in the ſame page; <hi>We do bleſs the Lord, we are not only a rod of Iron, to daſh the common enemies in pieces, but alſo a hedg (though very unworthy) about Chriſts vineyard: and if we know our own hearts, wherever the Lott of Gods Inheritance ſhall appear to be found in</hi> Scotland, <hi>we ſhall think it our duty, to the utmoſt of our lives to preſerve the ſame.</hi> Where the ſame ſpirit is in the Parliament and their Army, they will ſtill ſpeak the ſame language, and practiſe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
